<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sweiss&#39; Blog</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sweiss&#39; Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Mueller Report Volume 1: A Network Analysis </title>
      <link>/2019/07/21/mueller-report-volume-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/07/21/mueller-report-volume-1/</guid>
      <description>code
TLDR There are a lot of Russian’s talking to a lot of Trump campaign members in Mueller report. There are so many it’s tough to get your head around it all. In this post I attempted some network analysis on the relations between campaign officials and Russians. I found that one can ‘compress’ Russian involvement into 9 (mostly) distinct groups. I then summarize these points of contacts.
 Introduction to Mueller Report Volume 1 of Mueller Report starts with Russian interference in 2016 US Presidential Elections.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Much Have People Made on Bitcoin?</title>
      <link>/2018/04/03/how-much-have-people-made-on-bitcoin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/04/03/how-much-have-people-made-on-bitcoin/</guid>
      <description>Intro: How much has bitcoin made Society? This post will calculate the realized gains of bitcoin (up to year 2013) as a measure of how much society has made off of bitcoin.
 How are realized gains different from market capitalization? Realized gains measure the amount of money people can claim to have made off of bitcoin. This can be markedly different from the market capitalization.
For instance suppose we have two stocks A and B both with 100 shares and both with a price of $1 at time t_0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>November 2017 Auto Sales Predictions</title>
      <link>/2017/11/27/october-2017-auto-sales-predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/27/october-2017-auto-sales-predictions/</guid>
      <description>Previous Results Overall car sales for the month 5.7% lower than expected (predicted: 1436262, actual: 1356218). Porsche (new Cayenne and Panamera), Buick (Enclave and LaCrosse showed large gains), and Maserati (Levante) all showed strong growth.
Volvo saw weak numbers compared to the previously high growth they experienced. Both the XC60 and XC90 were expected to increase to 2200 and 3400 cars but fell to 1888 and 2550.
Audi was the most accurate prediction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>October 2017 Auto Sales Predictions</title>
      <link>/2017/10/29/october-2017-auto-sales-predictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/29/october-2017-auto-sales-predictions/</guid>
      <description>Below are predictions for 10-2017 autosales for each auto brand. I modeled monthley car sales by nameplate (eg Camry, Civic, etc), predicted one step ahead forecast and summed by manufacture. The model is a state-space model with trend and seasonality of 12.
  Manufacturers 2017-10-01    Acura 13434  Alfa 4174  Audi 19463  Bentley 147  BMW 24671  Buick 16098  Cadillac 16087  Chevrolet 188386  Chrysler 11397  Dodge 31470  Fiat 1889  Ford 201647  Genesis 2911  GMC 49994  Honda 117972  Hyundai 48862  Infinit 2597  Infiniti 12237  Jaguar 3599  Jeep 65997  Kia 54669  Land 7680  Lexus 27738  Lincoln 8837  Maserati 1024  Mazda 22668  Mercedes 20358  Mercedes-Benz 10691  Mini 3702  Mitsubishi 8867  Nissan 104120  Porsche 4199  Ram 45534  Scion 0  Smart 170  Subaru 53947  Tesla 4553  Toyota 185563  Volvo 10906  VW 28004    </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Uncertainty with Bayesian ML</title>
      <link>/2017/10/23/exploring-uncertainty-with-bayesian-ml/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/10/23/exploring-uncertainty-with-bayesian-ml/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: Bayesian machine learning techniques allow us to obtain a posterior density for individual predictions instead of just the mean. This additional information allows us to understand and explore the uncertainty involved. However not all uncertainties are the same; one could be certain the mean of a predicted value is a certain value but there could be high variance or one can not be certain of a particular prediction because the training set didn’t include values like the predicted input.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>pushing to master since 2012</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>